welcome back everybody I'm Dr Andy
Galpin and this is 5 minute fiz it's
really important that we end the
conversation of labeling exercises as
bad right this actually leads to a lot
of confusion and it takes a tool out of
the potential
toolbox so if we look at a picture like
this and you see a bunch of different
exercises and depending on what seminar
or clinic you went to you might here a
particular coach says something like you
should absolutely never ever ever do
this exercise it's bad for you and I
think that's tremendously shortsighted
in fact it does a disservice to the
field as as a whole so if we take a look
at any of those pictures and if I
started this video off by having you
look at those and say okay which one of
these is bad for you well depending on
who's looking at an athletic trainer or
a different strength coach with a
different philosophy you may get a
combination of different answers for
example if you look at the the
individual in the middle here who's
doing the the rounded deadlift well now
most of us are going to be in agreement
if he were to actually lift the weight
like that especially that heavy of a
weight it's probably going to be bad for
him but on the more towards the middle
of the spectrum I think is where the
most the confusion lies and you may hear
things like um you know front squats bad
for you and even now people are really
excited about talking about oh you
should never do crunches it's absolutely
bad for your back you should absolutely
never never never anytime we're talking
about things on that level of an
extreme you know you're going to have a
problem so it's I think it's
unproductive to say exercises are
absolutely out of the equation and you
can never do them and more beneficial to
talk about well when is this a risk or
how is this the risk and how can it be
helpful and that's what I want to do a
little bit of today so as I'm going
through this next section I want you to
picture any of these exercises or any
other exercise in mind that you've been
told is bad for you or maybe you
yourself actually think is bad and that
no one should ever
do so there's no bad exercises there's
only bad applications of exercises and I
have very four very specific criteria
that I feel like fall into the
application that can make a exercise bad
or harmful in this
case and that's generally improper
application in four forms either too
much volume intensity complexity
and or technique now a lot of the times
those first three problems can induce
the last one so for
example maybe doing front squats is not
a problem but if you did 6,000 front
squats a day that's potentially a
problem but I would say don't blame that
on the front squat don't call it a bad
exercise or it's harmful I would say you
did far too many repetitions of it and
that's your fault or your trainer's
fault or your coach's fault the same
thing with intensity for example doing a
front squat is not bad for you but doing
a front squat too heavy especially if it
elicits or induces a breakdown a
technique well again don't blame the
exercise blame the person prescribing it
or the person executing it that doesn't
mean we throw out the front squat for
everybody whoever who's ever going to
use it again or even for the rest of the
team or even for that person we just
make sure that we're prescribing it
properly so if we go back to our
original images and we went through any
one of these exercises um we'll just
take uh the overhead handstand pushup
okay so is an overhead
press a bad
exercise well because actually that's
what that individual in that picture is
doing he's just doing an overhead press
he happens to just be doing it upside
down and if I ask you all right
everybody take your hands like that put
a pencil in your hand and lift it up I
don't think anyone would call that a bad
exercise it's the same damn thing
what makes it bad is if you did too many
repetitions of it or you did it too
frequently if you do overhead pressing
four days a week or and you're also
throwing a javelin four days a week or
something else it's the volume of that
movement that gets you it's not the
movement itself so if you just reduce
the volume or the frequency you'd be
fine in that case as well some of us can
do overhand push-ups like that no
problem but if the movement itself is
too heavy if it represents too high of a
percentage of our pressing strength and
it becomes too
intense then maybe we have some problems
it's maybe simply too complex as well so
I took a basic overhead pressing
movement and I made it extremely complex
by making you do it upside
down or again any of those or
independently just breakdowns of
techniques so one elbow bang out
rotating of the shoulders forward
whatever else is a problem those can
cause issues with that overhead pressing
movement but it's not the fault of the
exercise it's the fault to the person
either programming it or the person
executing it so the key Point here no
exercise is permanently off limits I
will grant you if you're coaching say a
bunch of middle school players you may
say hey look I'm not going to do
overhead standing or or upside down
overhead pressing because I can't
control a room of 35 people at a time I
get it no problem that doesn't mean we
walk around telling people never under
any under any circumstances should a
high school kid ever overhead press or
whatever else so no exercise is
permanently off limits
though we may choose to use some of them
a little bit more selectively than
others thanks a lot and we'll see you
next time